I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we have the second in our
two-part series on anti-aging creams.
And we start with
a look at niacinamide,
also known as nicotinamide,
a form of vitamin B3.
I’ve talked about sunscreen
and topical retinoids.
What other skin cream components have
been shown to help with skin aging?
While placebo-controlled trials
are the standard in most medical research,
they are still all too rare
for cosmetic products.
This raises efficacy questions—
many are left with simply
buying “hope in a jar”—
as well as safety concerns.
Cosmetics to this day contain
an array of toxic chemicals.
Of the more than 12,000
synthetic chemicals used in cosmetics,
fewer than 20 percent
have been recognized as safe.
Of course, this doesn’t mean natural
ingredients are necessarily harmless.
Poison ivy is as natural
as you can get,
but you wouldn’t want
to rub in on your face.
However, there are some relatively
safe natural options
with varying degrees of efficacy.
In contrast to retinoic acid—
a form of vitamin A
that can be irritating—
topical niacinamide
(also known as nicotinamide)
is a form of vitamin B3
that is non-irritating
and found to be effective.
It’s been described
as one of the best studied
cosmeceutical ingredients
for anti-aging,
but it looks like there are only
two placebo-controlled human studies,
which gives you an idea of the state
of cosmeceutical science.
Skin photoaging is largely mediated
by UV-induced free radical formation.
One of the consequences
of excess sun exposure
is the oxidation of sugars and proteins
in the skin into yellow-brown pigment
that gives aging skin
a yellowing, sallow appearance.
Since niacinamide is a precursor
to two potent antioxidants,
the hope is that this process
could be interrupted,
and indeed the first published
study was entitled
“Topical niacinamide reduces yellowing,
wrinkling, red blotchiness,
and hyperpigmented spots
in aging facial skin.”
It was a 12-week, double-blind,
placebo-controlled,
randomized clinical split-face study
of middle-aged women.
In a split-face study,
each woman is her own control,
rubbing the active formulation
(in this case 5% niacinamide
in moisturizer) on one side of her face
and the placebo (straight moisturizer)
on the other half,
though neither she nor the researchers
know which side is which
until the code
is broken at the end.
This controls for skin type
and administration technique
(different people apply
facial products differently),
but participants often use the same hand
for applying the creams to both sides;
so, unless specified
that different gloves be worn,
or hands washed in between,
there can be cross-contamination.
Anyway, at the end of 12 weeks
there was a small, 5 percent reduction
in wrinkles and fine lines
and a slowing in the development
in blotchiness, spots, and sallowness.
A subsequent publication noted
an improvement in skin elasticity as well.
The magnitude of these
effects may only be
one-third to one-fifth
as good as retinoic acid,
but there were no reports
of excess skin irritation.
But use a four percent
concentration and application
was limited to crow’s feet wrinkles
around the eyes.
Significant reductions in wrinkles
by both subjective and objective measures
were noted by the end
of the eight-week study.
Sixty-four percent
of the niacinamide-side eye wrinkles
underwent moderate
or marked improvement
compared to zero percent
on the placebo-side eyes.
Finally today,
we look at the pros and cons
of alpha hydroxy acid lotions,
chemical peels,
and topical antioxidants
in reversing the
signs of aging.
There is a reason why
there is a long historical use
of fruit purees as facial masks,
and perhaps why Cleopatra
was said to bathe in sour milk.
Alpha hydroxy acids,
also known as fruit acids,
are natural acids found in foods.
They include citric acid (from citrus),
glycolic acid (from sugar cane),
lactic acid (from fermented fruits),
malic acid(from a variety of fruits),
and tartaric acid (from grapes).
High strength concentrations
are used for chemical peels.
Concentrations over 40%
can only be used by medical doctors.
Professionals in salons can give more
mild peels with 10 to 40% acid solutions,
but concentrations under 10% are sold
over the counter as exfoliants.
Alpha hydroxy acids are thought to work
by weakening cell-to-cell bonds
to hasten the shedding of dead cells
off the skin surface.
Three placebo-controlled studies
of over-the-counter strengths
have been published.
The first compared an 8% glycolic acid
lotion to an 8% lactic acid lotion
to a placebo lotion applied daily
on face and forearms for 22 weeks.
Both the acids worked similarly,
producing visible improvements
in facial photodamage in more than
70% of the acid groups
versus only 40% of the placebo group.
All the participants were advised
to wear protective clothing
and regularly use sunscreen,
which may help explain the benefits
even in the placebo group.
Overall forearm photodamage and sallowness
also improved significantly
in the acid versus placebo groups.
About 1 in 3 participants
experienced transient redness,
but only 1 (out of 74) left the study
due to facial irritation.
The second trial found a 5% glycolic acid
lotion for three months
beat out placebo on lessening skin
roughness and mottled discoloration
on the face and neck, but failed
to significantly reduce wrinkle scores.
The irony of alpha hydroxy acids is that
while they can help with past photodamage,
they can make future damage worse
by increasing skin photosensitivity.
So, taking precautions is recommended.
The FDA recommends that all
alpha hydroxy products
be labeled with a prominent warning:
Sunburn Alert: This product may increase
your skin’s sensitivity to the sun
and particularly
the possibility of sunburn.
Use a sunscreen,
wear protective clothing,
and limit sun exposure while using
this product and for a week afterwards.
What about ascorbic acid,
also known as vitamin C?
If niacinamide works
by turning into antioxidants,
why not just apply
antioxidants directly?
Topical application can lead
to vitamin E levels in the skin
10 times what is achieved by oral dosing
and vitamin C up to 40 times higher
(at least in mouse
and pig skin, respectively).
According to a review
on topical anti-aging skin care
by a prominent
Beverly Hills plastic surgeon,
“At a minimum, patients should be
encouraged to use daily sunscreen,
a topical retinoid every night,
and a topical antioxidant daily.”
But there’s only one antioxidant
that’s been clearly shown to work.
Despite its ubiquity
in skin care products,
there is no evidence
to support any role
for topical vitamin E in skin aging,
whether for wrinkles,
discoloration, or texture.
The one study on topical CoQ10
also failed to work
significantly better than placebo,
but there is one type of vitamin C
that has been shown to help.
Skin biopsy studies show
that the topical application
of a 5% solution of L-ascorbic acid
(also known as just ascorbic acid,
the type of vitamin C found in food)
significantly increases the expression
of collagen in human skin
compared to placebo,
suggesting “functional activity
of the skin cells
is not maximal in postmenopausal women
and can be increased.”
A split-face study
involving the application
of three drops of a 10% L-ascorbic
solution for three months
found significant improvements
over the placebo side of the face
in fine and coarse wrinkles,
sallowness, and skin tone or firmness.
Not knowing which side was which,
16 out of 19—84% of patients—
correctly identified the vitamin C side
as the one showing improvement.
Unfortunately, L-ascorbic acid
is unstable in creams,
turning an unsightly brown when
it oxidizes, limiting its shelf life;
so instead, the skin care industry
uses more stable vitamin C esters
or derivatives such as ascorbyl palmitate,
magnesium ascorbyl phosphate,
ascorbic acid sulfate,
ascorbyl stearate, etc.
Unfortunately, there is no evidence
that these compounds
have comparable effects,
likely because they are poorly absorbed
and only minimally
convert to the active form.
The good news is that
you can make your own.
Although vitamin C concentrations
as low as 3% or 5%
and have been shown
to have anti-wrinkle effects
in split face or split neck
and arm studies, 10% is recommended.
The 10% solution used in this study retails
for a ridiculous $127 per ounce.
You can make a DIY solution more than
two thousand times cheaper
simply by buying L-ascorbic acid in bulk
and mixing 3 grams into 30 grams of water
at a cost of about a nickel per ounce.
You can mix it in an eyedropper
and drip four to five drops
on the palm of your hand
and use your fingertips to apply over
your face, neck, and upper chest daily.
Just be careful to not
get any in your eyes.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.